資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, キャリア:career, 初め[はじめ]:beginning|first (in line, etc.)|origin|, 初め[ぞめ]:first doing of ... (ever, in one's life, in the new year, etc.)
（ヤサコ）コイルスの資料によると
ヌル･キャリアは初め―
According to the Coil data,
in the beginning, the Null Carrier
集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather, 探査[たんさ]:probe/inquiry/enquiry, 装置[そうち]:equipment/installation/apparatus
心のカケラを集める
探査装置だったそうです
was a radar device that collected pieces of souls.
女子[じょし, おなご]:woman/girl, 女子[めこ, メコ]:vagina|girl, 生徒[せいと]:pupil, 呼び出す[よびだす]:to summon/to call (e.g. phone)|to invoke (e.g. subroutine), たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
（女子生徒１）あの子が
ミチコさんを呼び出そうとしたって
That girl wanted to summon Miss Michiko!
女子[じょし, おなご]:woman/girl, 女子[めこ, メコ]:vagina|girl, 生徒[せいと]:pupil, ホント:truth/reality/actuality
（女子生徒２）
ホントなの？　ヤサコ
Is that true, Yasako?
（ヤサコ）
う… うん よく知らない
Um, I don't really know.
マユミ:Japanese spindle tree (Euonymus sieboldianus), はざま:interval/space|valley, 交差点[こうさてん]:crossing/intersection
前 マユミが言ってた
はざま交差点
Do you remember the Loophole Nexus you used to talk about, Mayumi?
教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
教えてほしいの
どうやって行ったの？
I'd like you to tell me how to get there.
今さら[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh
（マユミ）今さら？
After all this time?
必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
どうしても必要なの
I really need to know.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, 懸かる[かかる]:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang|to come into view||
友達の命が懸かってるの
My friend's life is in danger.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
（マユミ）それって本当に友達？
Is she really your friend?
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
（マユミ）私のときと同じで
Aren't you just pretending to be her friend, like you did with me?
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
あなたが友達のフリしてる
だけなんじゃないの？
マユミ:Japanese spindle tree (Euonymus sieboldianus)
（ヤサコ）マユミ…
Mayumi...
あのときは
聞きたくないって言ったくせに
Back then, you said, "I don't want to know."
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 無視[むし]:disregarding/ignoring
みんなと一緒に
私のこと無視したくせに
You ignored me, like everybody else did.
呪う[のろう]:to curse/to put a curse on/to detest intensely, 呪う[まじなう]:to pray that one avoids disaster or illness|to pray for the death or misfortune of another|to treat illness with prayer
“ミチコさんに呪われる”
とか言ってさ
I remember you said, "You'll be cursed by Miss Michiko."
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
怖かったの　だから…
I was frightened.
That's why...
You're always like that!
あなたは いつだってそう！
表向き[おもてむき]:outward appearance/ostensible/public, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, 裏[うら]:bottom (or another side that is hidden from view)|rear|lining||, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
表向きはいい顔して
裏では友達を呼び捨てしたりしてる
You're a goody two-shoes on the surface,
but you have no problem abandoning friends!
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly
ちゃんと知ってるんだから
I know all about it!
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
ずっと ずっと… あなたの
そういうところが嫌いだった
I always, always hated that about you.
優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle
優しいフリして…
You started out kind, but you didn't help me when I was in trouble.
困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered, 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
でも困ったときには
助けてくれなかった
だから 私は
自分でなんとかしたわ
So I worked it out myself somehow.
あなたもそうして
You should do the same.
怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular
（ハラケン）オバちゃん
怒ってるだろうな…
I guess Aunty's mad at me.
Kanazawa City
Loophole Nexus
通う[かよう]:to go to and from (a place)|to go to (school, work, etc.)|to circulate (e.g. blood, electricity)|, 道筋[みちすじ]:path/route/itinerary
あった！
ヤサコの通った道筋だ
Here!
This is the direction Yasako went.
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 癖[くせ, へき]:habit (often a bad habit, i.e. vice)|peculiarity|crease
にしても オバちゃんのメガネ
癖が強いな
Anyway,
Aunty's glasses are kinda quirky...
癖[くせ, へき]:habit (often a bad habit, i.e. vice)|peculiarity|crease, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（オバちゃん）
癖の強い女で悪かったわね
I'm sorry to be such a quirky woman!
私をナメるんじゃないわよ
Stop underestimating me.
ハード:hard, 位置[いち]:place/situation/position, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
自分のハードの位置くらい
３分で分かるわ
I certainly don't need more than three minutes to locate my own hardware.
マンホール:manhole, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
ヤサコは あのマンホールの場所に
行くつもりなんだ
Yasako wants to go to that manhole place.
止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
止めないと
If I don't stop her...
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（オバちゃん）
あのときのケンちゃんみたいに？
She'll end up like you did last time, huh?
中継[ちゅうけい]:relay/hook-up|relay broadcasting, 中継[なかつぎ]:joining/joint|mid-relief pitcher, ノード:node, 変える[かえる]:to change/to alter|to reform, もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 精度[せいど]:precision/accuracy, 上がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||
この中継ノードを変えれば
もっと精度が上がるわ
If we change this transmission node, it will become more accurate.
オ… オバちゃん？
Aunty?
手がかり[てがかり]:clue/lead|handhold, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
ヤサコは自分で
何か手がかりを見つけたのよ
Yasako found some kind of hint on her own.
懸ける[かける]:to hang (e.g. picture)|to sit|to take (time, money)||
彼女に懸けるしかないわ
All we can do is follow her.
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||
聞こえない もう道が分からない
I can't hear it.
I don't know the way anymore.
だから 私は
自分でなんとかしたわ
So I worked it out myself somehow.
あなたもそうして
You should do the same.
マユミ:Japanese spindle tree (Euonymus sieboldianus), とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
マユミの言うとおりだ
It's like Mayumi says.
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding, 痛み[いたみ]:pain/ache|damage, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 答え[こたえ, いらえ]:answer/reply/response
痛い… この痛みの先に答えがある
It hurts...
At the source of this pain, I'll find my answer.
霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray
あっ 霧だ
Fog!
コイル:coil, システム:system
（猫目(ねこめ)）金沢(かなざわ)にも
コイルシステムがあったのか
I didn't know there was a Coil system in Kanazawa too!
連れ帰る[つれかえる]:to bring (someone) back home/to take (someone) back home
今 もし 小此木(おこのぎ)が
天沢(あまさわ)を連れ帰ったら
If Okonogi manages to bring Amasawa back,
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 維持[いじ]:maintenance/preservation/improvement
空間を維持できなくなる
I won't be able to maintain the Space anymore.
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 始末[しまつ]:management|course of events|end result (usu. bad)|
早く始末をしなくては
We gotta get rid of her ASAP.
兄ちゃん[あんちゃん]:(my) older brother|sonny (with a nuance of suspicion)/lad, 兄ちゃん[にいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother", 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（タケル）兄ちゃん
あの子は何も悪くないんだ
Brother, she's not involved in this at all.
ヒドいことをしないで
Don't do anything bad to her!
ああ 分かってるさ
Yeah, I know.
The passage!
通路[つうろ]:passage/pathway/roadway
（ヤサコ）通路だわ
マユミ:Japanese spindle tree (Euonymus sieboldianus)
マユミが見たのは
これだったんだわ
This is the one Mayumi saw!
デバイス:device, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
（ヌル）
デバイスＩＤ 確認されました
The device ID has been recognized.
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 領域[りょういき]:area/domain/territory, アクセス:access
小此木先生
試験領域にアクセスしますか？
Doctor Okonogi, do you want to access the test area?
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
小此木先生？
Doctor Okonogi?
意識を失う[いしきをうしなう]:to lose consciousness, 主治医[しゅじい]:attending physician/physician in charge/(one's) family doctor, 医師[いし]:doctor/physician, 医師[くすし, くすりし]:doctor
（オバちゃん）
意識を失ったイサコの主治医は
小此木医師だった
Doctor Okonogi was in charge of Isako's treatment when she lost consciousness.
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 技術[ぎじゅつ]:technology|technique|art, 引き継ぐ[ひきつぐ]:to take over/to hand over, 解明[かいめい]:clarification/elucidation/explication, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
彼はコイルスの電脳技術を引き継ぎ
解明しようとしていた
He wanted to pass on his knowledge of cyberspace, and to make it understandable.
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
まさか ここまでとは
思っていなかったようだけど
However, he didn't expect anything like this to happen.
恐らく[おそらく]:perhaps/likely/probably, 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness
恐らく ヌルの正体は―
Most likely, each Null started out as a means of transportion called a Null Carrier.
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, キャリア:career, 乗り物[のりもの]:vehicle/conveyance|ride (playground, fair, carnival)
コイルスが作った
ヌル･キャリアという乗り物よ
キャリア:career
ヌル･キャリア？
A Null Carrier?
本来[ほんらい]:originally|essentially|proper, あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 引き上げる[ひきあげる]:to pull up|to increase|to withdraw||
（オバちゃん）本来は
あっちから情報を引き上げる―
In the beginning, it was an instrument to extract data from "the other side."
探査[たんさ]:probe/inquiry/enquiry, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
探査体だったらしい
改造[かいぞう]:remodeling/remodelling|modding, 加える[くわえる]:to add|to increase|to include|, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil, 現象[げんしょう]:phenomenon, 利用[りよう]:use/utilization/utilisation
でも 改造を加えるうち
電脳コイル現象を利用して
But, after further elaboration, it became a method
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), 送り込む[おくりこむ]:to send in
あっちへと意識を送り込み―
for sending consciousness to "the other side," exploiting the Dennou Coil phenomenon.
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 乗り物[のりもの]:vehicle/conveyance|ride (playground, fair, carnival)
電脳の乗り物として
使われるようになったのよ
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
今までの事故は―
The accidents that have occurred up till now are the result of abandoned Null and passages going wild.
放棄[ほうき]:abandonment/renunciation/resignation, 通路[つうろ]:passage/pathway/roadway, 暴走[ぼうそう]:acting rashly|runaway (process)|reckless baserunning, 結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition
放棄されたヌルと通路が
暴走した結果なのよ
本来[ほんらい]:originally|essentially|proper, 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, どおり:in accordance with/following|roughly, 恐らく[おそらく]:perhaps/likely/probably
でも 本来の
機能どおりに使えば 恐らく―
But if we use them the right way, maybe...
野生化[やせいか]:going feral (of a species)/reverting to wild/escape, 同じく[おなじく]:similarly/same (idea)/same (name), 通路[つうろ]:passage/pathway/roadway, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
あの野生化したヌルと同じく
通路に入れるはずよ
it'll be possible to enter the passage,
just like those wild Null.
（ハラケン）
じゃあ ヤサコはそれを？
You mean, Yasako wants to...
私有地[しゆうち]:demesne/estate/private land, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, 交差点[こうさてん]:crossing/intersection, 設置[せっち]:establishment/institution|installation (of a machine or equipment), してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
コイルスは私有地に
試験用の交差点を設置していた
Coil established a Nexus for experimental use in a private domain,
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 地名[ちめい]:place name, 名前をつける[なまえをつける]:to name
古い地名から名前をつけてね
taking the name from an existing geographic feature.
That's what the Loophole Nexus is.
はざま:interval/space|valley, 交差点[こうさてん]:crossing/intersection
それが“はざま交差点”
支社[ししゃ]:branch office, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
コイルスの金沢支社があった場所に
今もあるはずよ
It's where Coil's head office was located in Kanazawa.
It should still be there.
恐らく[おそらく]:perhaps/likely/probably, 通路[つうろ]:passage/pathway/roadway
そして 恐らく通路も…
And probably, the passage as well.
もうすぐだ
We're almost there!
ヤサコ！
Yasako!
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
遅かった
Too late!
（ハラケン）ハッ… ヌル！
Null?
正常[せいじょう]:normalcy/normality/normal
大丈夫 正常なヌルよ
It's all right. It's a regular Null.
This girl has just entered, hasn't she?
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.)
先にこの子が入ったわね？
Doctor Okonogi has logged into the experimental area.
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 領域[りょういき]:area/domain/territory, ログイン:login, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
（ヌル）小此木先生が
試験領域にログインしています
As I thought!
やはり:too/also|still
やはり…
（ハラケン）僕が行く
I'm going!
Null! Touch me!
触る[さわる]:to touch/to feel
（ハラケン）
ヌル 僕を触ってくれ！
デバイス:device, 一致[いっち]:coincidence|conformity|cooperation
（ヌル）
デバイスＩＤが一致しません
The device ID doesn't match.
You can only enter with Coil glasses.
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
コイルスのメガネでないと
入れないんだわ
（ハラケン）ハッ！
（オバちゃん）2.0！
2.0!
So they intend to destroy it from the inside?!
内部[ないぶ]:interior/inside/internal, 破壊[はかい]:destruction/disruption|(application) crash, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
（猫目）内部からも破壊する気か
Damn it! I've got no choice.
クソ！　こうなったら…
Even if I leave a record of my passage, all I can do is to enter by force.
足跡[あしあと, そくせき]:footprints|record of page visitors (e.g. in social networking sites), 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left, 強硬[きょうこう]:firm/strong/unbending, 手段[しゅだん]:means/way/measure
足跡は残るが
強硬手段でいくしかない！
What's this all about?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
（ハラケン）どういうこと？
The head office has started to act.
本社[ほんしゃ, ほんじゃ]:head office|main shrine|this company, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
（オバちゃん）
本社が動き始めたんだわ
In that case...
こうなったら…
追う[おう]:to chase|to follow (a set order, a trend, etc.)|to drive out||
タマ ヤサコを追うのよ！
Tama, chase Yasako.
（サッチー）ボク サッチー
Me Satchii!
本社[ほんしゃ, ほんじゃ]:head office|main shrine|this company, イマーゴ:imago, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being
本社は イマーゴと
電脳コイルの存在が―
The head office doesn't want to reveal the existence of Imago and Dennou Coil to the public.
世間[せけん]:world/society, 恐れる[おそれる]:to fear/to be afraid of
世間に知られるのを恐れている
じゃあ…
So...
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 中心[ちゅうしん]:center/centre|-centered, 中心[なかご]:core|tang (of a sword, etc.)|middle of a nest of boxes, 消す[けす]:to erase|to turn off power|to extinguish|, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
あっちの中心部を
ヤサコごと消す気だわ
They intend to destroy the core of it.
With Yasako inside.
そんな…
That can't be!
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
クソ！　遅かった
Crap! Too late!
I've taken over control.
コントロール:control, 奪う[うばう]:to snatch away/to dispossess/to steal, もみ消す[もみけす]:to stub out (e.g. a cigarette)/to crush out|to hush up, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
コントロールは奪った
もみ消し頼みます
Now, you erase the traces.
Two units have entered.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 内部[ないぶ]:interior/inside/internal, 基[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 基[き]:group|(free) radical|counter for installed or mounted objects (e.g. stone lanterns, gravestones, satellites)
次は内部の２基だな
子供[こども]:child/children
あとは
あの子供さえなんとかすれば…
If only I could dispose of that kid somehow...
兄ちゃん[あんちゃん]:(my) older brother|sonny (with a nuance of suspicion)/lad, 兄ちゃん[にいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"
兄ちゃん…
Brother...
Aunty! Yasako is inside.
オバちゃん ヤサコが中に！
落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||, パネル:panel, つなぐ:to connect/to link together|to tie, つなぐ:rigging
（オバちゃん）落ち着いて
タマのパネルをつないでみるわ
Calm down.
I'll try connecting to Tama's panel.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough
（猫目）よし
こちらもなんとか間に合った
Good.
Somehow, I managed to arrange it.
さあ あの子はどこだ？
Now, where's that kid?
センサー:sensor, うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|
チェッ センサーがうまく働かん
Damn... The sensors don't work properly!
兄ちゃん[あんちゃん]:(my) older brother|sonny (with a nuance of suspicion)/lad, 兄ちゃん[にいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother", やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
に… 兄ちゃん
やめようよ あの子は…
B-Brother, let's stop this.
That girl is...
黙る[だまる]:to be silent, かげん:(moon's) last quarter, かげん:lower limit|infimum, 口[くち]:mouth|opening|mouth (of a bottle)||, 口[く, こう]:mouth/speech|counter for people or implements, 塞ぐ[ふさぐ]:to stop up|to stand in the way|to occupy||
黙れ！　いいかげんにしないと
その口を塞ぐぞ！
Shut up!
If you don't stop bothering me, I'll seal that mouth of yours!
Δαιkoku City
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
痛いわ
It hurts...
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
見つけたぞ
Gotcha!
（発射音）
（ヤサコ）わあっ…
こしゃく:impudent
（猫目）クソ！　こしゃくな…
Crap! How impudent!
Unable to identify domain
Cannot Restore
手動[しゅどう]:manual (operation), 修復[しゅうふく, しゅふく]:restoration/repair/mending
タケル 手動で修復だ
Takeru! Try a manual restore!
兄ちゃん[あんちゃん]:(my) older brother|sonny (with a nuance of suspicion)/lad, 兄ちゃん[にいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"
わ… 分かったよ 兄ちゃん
O-Okay, brother.
（ヤサコ）あっ サッチー？
Satchii?
（ハラケン）僕だ　ハラケンだ
It's me, Haraken!
Eh?
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
（オバちゃん）ヤサコ 聞こえる？
Yasako, can you hear me?
オバちゃん
Aunty!
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious
（オバちゃん）
ハァ… うまくいったわ
Good, it worked.
（ヤサコ）どうしてタマが？
Why is Tama...
アカウント:account, 消去[しょうきょ]:elimination/erasure/dying out
私のアカウントは消去されたけど
My account was deleted,
裏口[うらぐち]:backdoor/rear entrance, 気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
ケンちゃんの裏口が
気づかれずに残ってたのよ
but Ken's back door wasn't discovered.
ヤサコ 僕だ
Yasako, it's me!
Haraken! Thank goodness.
目が覚める[めがさめる]:to awaken/to perk up/to snap out (of something)
ハラケン…
よかった 目が覚めたのね
You finally woke up.
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
（ハラケン）
うん 僕のことは もう心配ないよ
Yup.
There's no need to worry about me anymore.
飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump
飛んでる
We're flying...
持ち出す[もちだす]:to take out/to carry out|to mention something, いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), 手を加える[てをくわえる]:to perform some process/to apply some treatment|to revise
（オバちゃん）持ち出すとき
いろいろ手を加えたのよ
I added various functions when I took it out.
大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
大人としては
あとが大変だけどね
Although as an adult, I'll end up having to pay for this.
どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
（ハラケン）
でも どっちに向かえば…
But,
where should we go?
（イサコ）ここは…
Where am I?
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
お兄ちゃん
Brother...
階段[かいだん]:stairs/stairway/staircase
そうだ この階段の上…
Right,
at the top of these stairs...
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
そこにいるのね？　お兄ちゃん
You're there, aren't you!
Brother!
（信彦(のぶひこ)）勇子(ゆうこ) 勇子…
Yuko.
お母さん[おかあさん]:mother, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
（幼少のイサコ）
見て お母さんが作ってくれたの
Look.
Mom made these!
人形[にんぎょう]:doll/puppet/figure, お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
このお人形は お兄ちゃんと私
These two dolls are my brother and me.
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
だから 私のこと忘れないでね
So, don't forget about me!
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
（信彦）忘れないさ
勇子こそ 僕のこと忘れるなよ
I sure won't.
And you too, Yuko, don't forget about me.
お母さん[おかあさん]:mother, 時々[ときどき]:sometimes/at times, 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
お母さん 時々 怖いの
Sometimes, I'm afraid of Mama.
She hits me.
私のこと ぶつの
泣く[なく]:to cry/to weep/to sob
（信彦）泣いちゃダメだ イサコ
You mustn't cry, Isako.
イサコ？
Isako?
秘密[ひみつ]:secret|secret|esoteric teachings, 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher
ああ 秘密の暗号名だ
Yup, it's your secret code name.
勇ましい[いさましい]:brave/valiant|stirring
勇子のユウは 勇ましいのユウ
Yuko's "Yu" stands for "isamashii," courageous.
だからイサコ
（イサコ）うん
Hence, Isako.
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 秘密[ひみつ]:secret|secret|esoteric teachings, 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher
（信彦）僕だけがそう呼ぶ
秘密の暗号だよ
It's a secret code name, so only I can call you that.
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 秘密[ひみつ]:secret|secret|esoteric teachings
じゃあ お兄ちゃんの
秘密の名前は？
Then what's your secret name?
そうだな… 僕は４４２３
Let me see...
I'm 4-4-2-3.
４４２３？
4-4-2-3?
別れ[わかれ]:parting/separation/farewell
（信彦）
さあ もうすぐお別れの時間だ
Well, it's about time to depart.
遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys
上で遊ぼう イサコ
Let's go play upstairs.
Yeah!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
お兄ちゃん…
Brother!
Yasako!
（ハラケン）ヤサコ どうしたの？
What's wrong?
My chest...
胸[むね, むな]:chest|breasts|heart||, 痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
胸が… 心が痛い
My heart hurts.
天沢さん… 天沢さんなの？
Amasawa...
Is that you, Amasawa?
You mustn't falter.
迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|, 進む[すすむ]:to advance|to precede|to make progress||, 進む[すさむ]:to grow wild/to run to waste
（ミチコ）迷ってはダメ
そのまま進むのよ 勇子
You must go straight on, Yuko.
Welcome back, Yuko.
おかえり:return|welcome home
（信彦）おかえり 勇子
Brother!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
お兄ちゃん！
That direction...
方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action)
この方向…
Tama, go that way!
方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 進む[すすむ]:to advance|to precede|to make progress||, 進む[すさむ]:to grow wild/to run to waste
タマ この方向に進んで
Yasako! Did you learn something?
（ハラケン）
ヤサコ 何か分かったの？
I'm sure...
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, この先[このさき]:beyond this point/from now on/after this
きっと… きっとこの先に
天沢さんがいる
I'm sure I'll find Amasawa over there.
In the direction of the pain I feel in my heart.
胸[むね, むな]:chest|breasts|heart||, 痛み[いたみ]:pain/ache|damage, 感じる[かんじる]:to feel/to sense/to experience, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action)
胸が痛みを感じる方向に
The direction the pain is coming from?
痛み[いたみ]:pain/ache|damage, 感じる[かんじる]:to feel/to sense/to experience, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action)
痛みを感じる方向？
I don't really know why,
もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
（ヤサコ）なぜだか分からないけど
天沢さんにもらったキラバグが…
but the kirabug Amasawa gave me...
The encode in my chest tells me so.
胸[むね, むな]:chest|breasts|heart||, 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
胸の暗号が 私にそう教えるの
I don't know what will happen.
どうなるか分からない…
But I'm the only one who can save Amasawa now.
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
でも 私しか
もう天沢さんを助けられない
ヤサコ
Yasako...
If I stop believing I can save Amasawa,
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
私が天沢さんがまだ生きてることを
信じられなくなったら
she really won't be able to come back anymore.
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
天沢さんは本当に戻れなくなる
I'm the only one...
私だけが…
I understand, Yasako.
分かったよ ヤサコ
Haraken...
（ヤサコ）ハラケン
But promise me
約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
でも約束して 必ず戻るって
that you'll definitely come back.
That you'll definitely come back with Amasawa.
連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person), 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 戻ってくる[もどってくる]:to come back
イサコも連れて
絶対 戻ってくるって
Okay, I promise.
約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny
うん 約束する
Hurry up, Tama.
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
急いで タマ
Geez...
まったく:really/truly|indeed, 保護者[ほごしゃ]:guardian/protector/patron, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
まったく… あんたたちの
保護者やるのも大変だわ
It's hard being your guardian.
But, I wonder if there really is a way out.
出口[でぐち]:exit/gateway/way out
でも 出口はあるのかな？
This sensation...
感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
この感じ…
これは天沢さんの気持ちなの？
Are these Amasawa's feelings?
These kinda sad, lonely...
悲しい[かなしい]:sad/sorrowful, 切ない[せつない]:painful/heartrending|oppressive
この悲しくて切ないような
Yasako, I got a reply to the ping!
反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response
（ハラケン）
ヤサコ 反応が出た！　下だ
Down there!
A town.
街[がい]:.. street/.. quarter/.. district, 街[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||
（ヤサコ）街だわ
A deserted town.
無人[むじん, ぶにん]:lack of help|unmanned/uninhabited, 街[がい]:.. street/.. quarter/.. district, 街[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||
ここも無人の街だわ
Daikoku City
This is...
大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 市[いち]:market/fair, 市[し]:city
ここ 大黒市(だいこくし)？
Daikoku City?
Run, Yasako!
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
（ハラケン）逃げろ ヤサコ！
You sure give me a lot of trouble, Tamako.
やってくれる:to come along/to come around|to arrive at the present, 玉子[たまご]:eggs|hen egg|(an expert) in the making|
（猫目）やってくれるな 玉子(たまこ)
I'll have you arrested straight away.
手を回す[てをまわす]:to make the necessary preparations in secret, 逮捕[たいほ]:arrest/apprehension/capture
すぐに手を回して逮捕してやる
However,
くたびれる:to get tired/to be exhausted|to wear out, ポンコツ:piece of junk (esp. dismantled or broken down car)/worn-out article, 性能[せいのう]:ability/performance/efficiency, 差[さ]:difference/variation|difference, 差[さし, サシ]:between (e.g. two people)|hindrance|arrhythmic section of recitative in noh music||, 思い知る[おもいしる]:to realize/to realise
だが そのくたびれたポンコツに
性能の差を思い知らせてやる！
first I'll let you see the difference between my skills and that crappy piece of junk.
（ハラケン）ヤサコ！
Yasako!
旧式[きゅうしき]:old type/old style
この旧式が！
This damn outdated stuff!
タマ？
Tama?
タマ！
Tama!
限定[げんてい]:limit/restriction, フォーマット:(computer) format
チッ こうなったら
限定フォーマットで…
At this point, with the limited format...
ク… クソ！
Crap!
取り逃がす[とりにがす]:to miss (capturing)/to fail to catch/to let slip
取り逃がしたか
She got away.
Unauthorized access detected
タケル お前 何かしたのか？
Takeru...
Did you do something?
気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
（タケル）
ヤサコを殺す気だったんだね
Yasako...
You tried to kill her just now, right?
父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, 母さん[かあさん, かかさん]:mother|wife (used when speaking to or about one's own wife)
くっ… 父さんと母さんのためだ
It's for Dad and Mom.
父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, イマーゴ:imago, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation
父さんはイマーゴを開発して
Dad developed the Imago,
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., 集合[しゅうごう]:gathering/assembly|set, 無意識[むいしき]:unconsciousness|the unconscious, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 化[か]:action of making something/-ification
世界で初めて人間の集合無意識を
電脳空間化したんだ
and was the first person in the world to channel concentrated human consciousness into cyberspace.
発明[はつめい]:invention|intelligent|being enlightened, 奪う[うばう]:to snatch away/to dispossess/to steal
それなのに
メガマスはその発明を奪って
And despite that,
Megamass stole his discovery and got rid of us like garbage!
捨てる[すてる]:to throw away|to abandon|to give up, 家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew
ゴミのように捨てた
僕ら家族全員を！
Our entire family!
病気[びょうき]:illness/disease/sickness, 母さん[かあさん, かかさん]:mother|wife (used when speaking to or about one's own wife), 救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save
それに病気の母さんを救うには―
So,
in order to save our sick mother, we must reclaim our father's honor!
父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, 名誉[めいよ]:honor/honour/credit, 取り戻す[とりもどす]:to take back/to regain/to get back
父さんの名誉を
取り戻すしかないんだ
お前だって分かってるだろ！
You know that too, don't you?!
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 滅ぶ[ほろぶ]:to be ruined/to go under/to perish
（ミチコ）この世界は
もうすぐ滅ぶはずだったの
This world was about to disappear.
あちこち:here and there/all around|to get things in the wrong order (back to front), 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through, 始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
あちこちが壊れ始めて
It was destined
兄弟[きょうだい, けいてい]:siblings|brothers|siblings-in-law|, 運命[うんめい]:fate/destiny/lot
私も兄弟たちも
みんな死んでいく運命だった
to crumble here and now,
and your brother and I to die.
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
でも あの人が助けてくれた
But,
that person saved us.
（イサコ）あの人？
That person?
（ミチコ）宗助(そうすけ)よ
Sosuke.
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise), 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
この世界を守るために
何が必要かを教えてくれた
He taught me what I had to do to save this world.
復讐[ふくしゅう]:revenge, してやる:to do for (someone)
（猫目）復讐(ふくしゅう)してやる
メガマスをズタズタにしてやる！
I'll get my revenge.
I'll tear Megamass to shreds!
必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
そのためにミチコが必要なんだ
That's why I need Michiko.
（タケル）何をするつもりなの？
What do you... intend to do?
利用[りよう]:use/utilization/utilisation
あのアバズレを利用して
I'll use that bitch
世界中[せかいじゅう]:around the world/throughout the world, イマーゴ:imago, 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, してやる:to do for (someone)
世界中のイマーゴのガキどもを
意識不明にしてやるんだ
to make all the kids in the world lose consciousness.
そんなこと…
But that's awful!
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 維持[いじ]:maintenance/preservation/improvement
あの空間を維持しなければならない
I must control that Space.
そのために
勇子をミチコにくれてやったんだ
That's why I gave Yuko to Michiko.
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, せいにする:to lay the blame on/to put the fault on, 終わり[おわり]:the end
全部 メガマスのせいにしてやる
これでヤツらも終わりだ！
I'll make it seem like it's all Megamass' fault.
And that will be the end of them!
兄ちゃん[あんちゃん]:(my) older brother|sonny (with a nuance of suspicion)/lad, 兄ちゃん[にいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother", 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
兄ちゃん 僕はもう手伝えない！
Brother...
I...
I can't help you anymore!
待て タケル！
Wait, Takeru!
父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, 敵を討つ[かたきをうつ, あだをうつ]:to avenge (somebody) by striking down their killer
バカめ！
父さんの敵を討ちたくないのか！
You fool! Don't you want to take revenge for Dad?
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
（メガばあ）うむ それにしても
この空間は 一体…
Of all things, I wonder what this Space could possibly be...
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
（イサコの叔父）
そのことでお話があります
I have to tell you something about this.
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 奥様[おくさま]:wife/your wife/his wife
先生の奥様ですね？
You're Dr. Okonogi's wife, aren't you?
葬儀[そうぎ]:funeral service, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree
ご葬儀のとき 一度…
We met once, at the funeral.
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry
（ミチコ）でも あなたは
何も気にしなくていいのよ
But you don't have to worry about anything.
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
この空間が
一体なんのためにあるのか
Don't worry about why this Space is here,
なぜできたのか 私にも分からない
or why it was created.
I don't know either.
お兄さん[おにいさん]:older brother/elder brother|(vocative) young man, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
でも あなたが
ここでお兄さんと一緒に―
But if you will just live here happily, with your brother,
幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck, 暮らす[くらす]:to live/to get along|to spend (time)
幸せに暮らすことで
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise), 永遠[えいえん]:eternity/perpetuity/immortality
この世界は守られる 永遠に…
this world will be saved.
Forever.
ここだわ
They're here...
鳥居[とりい]:torii/Shinto shrine archway, 階段[かいだん]:stairs/stairway/staircase
鳥居の階段だわ
The stairs with torii!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
お兄ちゃん ずっと一緒だよね？
Brother, you'll always stay with me, won't you?
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
ああ ずっと一緒だ
Yes, always.
（イサコ）あっ
（信彦）どうしたの？
What's wrong?
分かんない…
I don't know.
天沢さん！
Amasawa!
（ミチコ）ダメよ 勇子
No, Yuko.
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
誰かが呼んでるの
Someone is... calling me.
空耳[そらみみ]:mishearing|(feigned) deafness|homophonic translation of song lyrics for comic effect
（ミチコ）それは空耳よ
You're just hearing things.
違うわ
No!
耳を傾ける[みみをかたむける]:to lend an ear/to hearken/to give an ear to
（ミチコ）耳を傾けてはダメ 勇子
You don't have to listen to it, Yuko.
That voice will devastate your happiness.
答える[こたえる]:to answer/to reply
いる そこにいるのね？
天沢さん 答えて！
You're there, aren't you?
Amasawa! Answer!
誰？　誰なの？
Who...
Who is it?
（ミチコ）
勇子 勇子 どこに行くの？
Yuko.
Yuko,
where are you going?
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
この空間が壊れたら
If this Space collapses, your brother will die.
お兄さん[おにいさん]:older brother/elder brother|(vocative) young man, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
あなたのお兄さんも
死んでしまうの
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
勇子 あなたが
この世界を守らなくてはならない
Yuko,
you have to protect this world.
あの女は―
That girl
お兄さん[おにいさん]:older brother/elder brother|(vocative) young man, 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck, 暮らす[くらす]:to live/to get along|to spend (time), 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
お兄さんと幸せに暮らせる
この世界を壊そうとしているのよ
intends to destroy this world, where you can live happily with your brother.
なぜ そんなことを？
Why such...
ご覧[ごらん]:(please) try to|(please) look|seeing, なさる:to do
（ミチコ）ご覧なさい 勇子
Look at this, Yuko.
嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
なぜ あなたが
あの子を嫌いなのか
See why you hate that girl.
拒絶[きょぜつ]:refusal/rejection
なぜ あの子を
拒絶しなくてはならないのか
The reason why you should reject her.
もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
名前をもらったのは
あなただけじゃなかった
In fact, you weren't the only one to receive a name.
名付ける[なづける]:to name/to call/to christen
あなたに
“イサコ”と名付けたように
Just like he gave you a name, he gave one to that other girl, too. "Yasako".
名付ける[なづける]:to name/to call/to christen
あの子にも“ヤサコ”と名付けた
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（イサコ）やめて…
Stop it!
（ミチコ）それだけじゃない
That girl stole your dear brother from you.
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 奪う[うばう]:to snatch away/to dispossess/to steal
あなたの大事なお兄ちゃんを
あの子は奪ったのよ
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
あなたがお兄ちゃんを
取られたくないという気持ち
Your fear that your brother would be taken away...
憎む[にくむ]:to hate/to detest, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
あなたが あの子を憎む気持ち
Your hatred for that girl...
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, 生まれる[うまれる]:to be born
その気持ちから 私は生まれたの
I was born from those feelings.
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
思い出したわ
I remember.
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle, 包む[つつむ]:to wrap up/to tuck in|to conceal, 包む[くるむ]:to wrap up/to tuck in/to pack
（ミチコ）この世界だけが
あなたを優しく包んでくれる
This is the only world that can protect you.
壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
あの子は
それを壊そうとしているの
And she's trying to destroy it.
そんなことさせない
I won't let her...
do anything like that!
誰？
Who is it?
（イサコ）来ないで！
Don't come here!
天沢さん！
Amasawa!
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough
天沢さん 帰りましょう！
今なら間に合う
Amasawa, let's go back!
If we go now, we'll make it in time!
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 居場所[いばしょ]:whereabouts/place|place where one belongs
（イサコ）帰って！
私の居場所は もうここしかないの
Go away!
This is the only place where I can possibly live now!
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
戻っても 私は
お兄ちゃんを死なせた―
If I go back, I'll be nothing more than the stupid kid who killed her brother!
妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend
バカな妹になるだけ
天沢さん！
Amasawa!
（イサコ）イヤ！
No!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 暮らす[くらす]:to live/to get along|to spend (time), ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
ここで
お兄ちゃんと暮らすの ずっと…
I will live here with my brother.
Forever.
大っ[おお]:big/large, 大っ[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||
もう来ないで！　大っ嫌い！
Don't come any closer!
I HATE YOU!
That's right.
憎む[にくむ]:to hate/to detest
（ミチコ）それでいいのよ
あの子を憎むのよ 勇子
You must hate that girl, Yuko.
誰？　あなたは誰なの？
Who...
Who are you?
言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech
天沢さん
その子の言葉を聞いてはダメ！
Amasawa, you don't have to listen to that girl!
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
（イサコ）帰って！
Go away!
コイル:coil, ドメイン:domain, 崩壊[ほうかい]:collapse/crumbling|decay
コイルドメインが崩壊する
The Coil Domain is...
collapsing!
ヤサコ！
Yasako!
（ミチコ）これでよかったのよ
It's for the best.
望む[のぞむ]:to desire|to wish for|to see
これは あなたが…
勇子が望んだことなのよ
It's what you wished for, Yuko.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 暮らす[くらす]:to live/to get along|to spend (time)
ここで一緒に暮らしましょう
Let's live here together.
永遠[えいえん]:eternity/perpetuity/immortality
３人で永遠に…
The three of us, forever.
（イサコ）違う 何かが違うわ…
Something...
has gone wrong.
It wasn't like this.
リンク:link/directory entry, 途切れる[とぎれる]:to pause/to be interrupted
（オバちゃん）リンクが途切れた
The link has been disconnected.
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
そんな… 空間は？
How terrible! And the Space?
分からない
I don't know.
完全[かんぜん]:perfection/completeness, リンク:link/directory entry, 切れる[きれる]:to break|to be injured|to wear out||
でも 今は
完全にリンクが切れている
But at present, the link is completely disconnected.
じゃあ ヤサコはどうなるの？
So what will become of Yasako?
リンク:link/directory entry, 切れる[きれる]:to break|to be injured|to wear out||
ヤサコとのリンクも切れたわ
The link to Yasako is disconnected too.
Yasako!
目を覚ます[めをさます]:to wake up|to sober up/to come to one's senses
ヤサコ！　ヤサコ 目を覚まして！
Yasako! Open your eyes!
プレゼント:present/gift
（静江(しずえ)）
おじいちゃんのプレゼントよ
It's a present from Grandpa.
（幼少のヤサコ）
わあー ハハ！
かわいそう:poor/pitiable/pathetic
（親戚のおばあさん）
かわいそうにねえ…
How sad.
Just as his granddaughter had come to visit.
やっと:at last/at length|barely, 孫[まご]:grandchild
やっと孫が来たのに
（デンスケ）ク～ン…
可愛い[かわいい, かわゆい]:cute|dear|cute little
（幼少のヤサコ）わあー 可愛い！
How cute!
（デンスケ）ク～ン ク～ン…
わあ…
大好き[だいすき]:loveable/very likeable/like very much
大好き！
I love you so much!
（ヤサコ）ウンチ！
Poop!
Densuke...
デンスケ…
What can we do?
迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|
どうしよう… 迷っちゃった
I got lost.
I already passed by here.
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||
ここ さっきも通ったわ
These are my memories.
記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage
これは私の記憶だわ
記憶を見てるんだ
I'm looking at my memories!
あのときの…
This is the...
Null Carrier
キャリア:career
これって ヌル･キャリア？
from back then?
I remember.
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
（イサコ）思い出した
That time...
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
あのとき 私はお兄ちゃんと…
I was with my brother, and...
Yuko.
（ミチコ）勇子
We were about to disappear.
消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear
（イサコ）消えそうになってた
Right.
全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear
そうだわ 全ては
あのまま消えるはずだった
Everything should have disappeared at that time.
You don't need to remember.
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
（ミチコ）思い出してはダメ
Brother?
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
お兄ちゃん？
Soon I won't be able to be your brother anymore.
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
もうじき 僕は
君のお兄ちゃんではいられなくなる
From now on, you'll have to learn how to live without me.
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
これからは 僕なしで
生きていかなくてはならないんだ
Brother! I don't want to be separated from you!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother)
お兄ちゃん 別れたくない！
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
（イサコ）思い出した
I remember!
I had to part from my brother forever!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, さよなら:good-bye
私は お兄ちゃんと
さよならするはずだった
But...
それなのに…
That height...
背[せい]:height/stature, 背[せ]:back|reverse|height|, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance
この背の高さ
もしかして…
Maybe...
What are you looking for?
捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
あなたは
何を捜してるの？
4-4-2-3...
（ヌル）…ニイ サン
Huh?
4-4-2-3.
…ニイ サン
Brother?
Note - 2-3 is said the same way as the word for "Brother"
兄さん[にいさん, あにさん]:older brother|brother (as older-brother figure in friendly and or work relationship)|(vocative) young man
兄さん？
I'm looking for 4-4-2-3.
私ハ…
４４２３ ヲ 捜シテイル
Yes,
ソウダ 私ハ…
with the Coil cure I can treat 4-4-2-3...
医療[いりょう]:medical care/medical treatment, 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||
コイルス ノ 医療機デ
４４２３ヲ…
Searching for the link destination
The link hasn't reconnected yet.
相変わらず[あいかわらず]:as ever/as usual/the same, リンク:link/directory entry, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（オバちゃん）
相変わらず リンクは戻らない
If it keeps on like this...
このままじゃ…
Mega-baa, any clues?
メガばあ 何か手はないの？
Hmm, I'm in Isako's hospital room right now.
病室[びょうしつ]:sickroom/hospital room
（メガばあ）
うむ 今 イサコの病室じゃ
What?
（オバちゃん）なんですって？
Isako's uncle called me.
叔父[おじ, はくふ]:uncle, 叔父[おとおじ]:uncle (one's father's younger brother), 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
（メガばあ）
イサコの叔父に呼ばれてな
I'm accessing all the data right now.
全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, 目を通す[めをとおす]:to scan/to look over
今 全ての資料に
目を通しておるわ
んっ？
信彦が４４２２？
Nobuhiko Amasawa?
4-4-2-2?
What does this mean?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
どういうことじゃ？
And what's more, the date of his death is shown
死亡[しぼう]:death/mortality|to die, 時期[じき]:time/season|soon, 交通事故[こうつうじこ]:traffic accident, 直後[ちょくご]:immediately following
それも死亡時期は
交通事故の直後…
as immediately after the accident!
これを見い
This is... 4-4-2-3's clinical record!
カルテ:patient's chart/clinical records
（オバちゃん）
これは４４２３のカルテ
It's about Isako's brother, Nobuhiko Amasawa, huh.
兄[あに]:elder brother/older brother, 兄[けい]:elder brother|pronoun or suffix used in reference to an older brother figure/Mister
イサコの兄 天沢信彦のものね
Not at all!
見落とす[みおとす]:to overlook/to fail to notice/to miss (seeing)
（オバちゃん）いいや 違う
わしも見落としておった
I didn't notice either.
Look at the patient's name.
患者[かんじゃ]:(a) patient
患者の名前を見てみい！
The name?
名前？
4-4-2-3 is that boy?
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
４４２３って
あのお兄ちゃん？
No.
違ウ
I'm looking for 4-4-2-3,
私ハ ４４２３ヲ…
Amasawa Yuko.
天沢勇子 ヲ 捜シテイル
Amasawa... Yuko?
（オバちゃん）
天沢勇子？
Yeah, 4-4-2-3 is...
（メガばあ）
ああ ４４２３とは…
none other than Isako herself!
自身[じしん]:by oneself/personally
イサコ自身だったのじゃ
Preview
Next time
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil, 最終[さいしゅう]:last/final/closing, 回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||
（ヤサコ）次回
「電脳コイル」最終回
on Dennou Coil:
The last episode...
Yasako and Isako.
Yasako and Isako
〝ヤサコとイサコ 〞
See you next time!
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
お楽しみに